okay um hello everyone i'm jun i'm the instructor for this workshop uh g8k
variant calling so welcome everyone uh so for now does everyone mind turning on
your camera just so that i i know who you are you're there hi okay so
uh before we start it seems like we have a very small crowd so that's that's good i guess
um so uh just a like a little bit about myself so i think at first we can
maybe go around since just there's just a few of us it's very easy to quickly go around and introduce ourselves quickly
so my name is jun i am a postdoc in the eeb department at ucla uh i work
with curclomular my population geneticist and anthropological geneticist
i got my degree in anthropology and now i study human population genetics stuff related to archaic humans and also
modern human evolution so do we want to
quickly go around and tell me which institute or department you're
from um what is your favorite biological question
like i'm not sure if everybody here is graduate student or some some of you may be like undergrad or faculty like i'm not sure
so just tell us a little bit about yourself and also um i know not everybody fill out the the
questionnaire on google form and that's okay so just in a few words just tell me what's your
main goal of attending this workshop like like if you're trying to be an dtk expert if you have your own data
or you're trying to work on like right now or you're just trying to get a brief understanding so just
just like a little bit so that i know what to what to get ready for um
do i have a volunteer that wants to start okay i'll go first yeah so my name is
omari and i'm from cornell university and i'm studying biomedical engineering
phd i'm currently in my second year and i'm very interested in the use of selfie dna to study infectious
diseases but i'm very new to this topic and to
the field in general so i figured it's a good skill to learn
yeah that sounds great um i can go next sure
hi i'm rohan uh i have a background in bioinformatics mostly i've worked with like rnac data
and like while so i was working at wild cornell and now i have moved to case western over here
so now i am working with like imaging data so my primary interests are like kind of like integrated research like in
imaging and omix and uh i have always like wanted to work with like different kinds of omix datasets so
uh i'm like always like trying to learn like different omics like single cell rnases and they
call it so data sets and like different kinds of omx datasets although i am kind of like
familiar familiar with these technologies and like i have seen people working with like variants and things
but yeah i haven't really like gone like a deep dive and learn how to
like process these things and like how what do they mean basically snips and
all these kind of things so yeah yeah that sounds great and i think what you're good at is something i don't
really know like i don't really work on rnc but that sounds cool yeah it'll be good uh
anyone else next i can go next guys my name is kim i am also a second
year phd student like omari um i'm in the anthropo department sorry a
truck is coming by i'm in the anthropology department at ucla and i study human genetics and
epigenetics and i've been kind of going down like a selection scan wormhole
lately yeah yeah it's hard i saw that you work with abby
right yeah yeah say hi to her i haven't seen her in a year oh yeah that's so cool i didn't know you
guys knew each other yeah we barely met right before the pandemic started and and like we said well let's get
coffee at some point and then we never see each other again oh yeah she's super busy she has like
two kids yeah yeah that's really cool though cool um
what else yeah i can hear you so i'm a postdoc at cedars my name is sarona i don't have my
camera in my lap that's fine so i just i'm just taking this workshop
to learn about uh the variant calling and stuff yeah just out of interest yeah cool
yeah um and we see we have a new person joining us uh hi
mohammed are you there
um okay yeah um if you have uh
do you have your camera or do you like uh or do you have your microphone like i
mean if not that's fine like we're just quickly going around to introduce ourselves that that's okay
yeah no worries um yeah and again i'm june i'm teaching
this workshop so okay uh so now that we briefly know each other oh he typing
sorry he does this okay that that's okay so so um before we
start i just wanted to uh like go over some quick like
housekeeping stuff um so uh everything we're going to cover for the next two days are going to be
recorded um so just to avoid some uh interactive issues with with zoom
uh i'd like you to have yourself muted most of the time um when i'm sharing my screen i actually
can't really see the chat box like i realize that so if you have questions feel free to
interrupt me just add me to yourself at that time just say i have a question stop there like i was out there but you
just like if you type in the chat box while i'm sharing my screen i can't really see that i won't even
i think i won't even know there's there's like a there's a message um so it's actually my first time
teaching this workshop so i have everything prepared um what i don't know and i like
is like how much realistic i can cover in three hours so if i'm going very fast or too slow uh
feel free to let me know and my plan is to have
the backbone of gatk covered today and go over some of the details with
like like like how to deal with vcs and how to clean that tomorrow and maybe do more like question like q a
things tomorrow so that's that's a plan but i may not exactly follow that depending on how how things go like i realistically i
don't really know how long it takes to cover all my slides so let's let's try and start
all right so oh before we start is everybody on uh hoffman right now
okay uh so uh i will start with some lectures but at some point uh i think it will be
cool that would so since there's just a few of us like we each get on huffman and type something so i
can share my screen on my end and and just to see if everything will go like we
we won't actually run real analysis during these three hours because some things will take more than three hours to finish um
but at least we can cover the basic commands so if you have your
terminal or or whatever command line open that will be very convenient um so let's start
okay is everybody seeing my slide sounds good okay
we went over this already okay so this is the schedule for the next
uh two days um so i will uh especially today i will go with some
lectures especially for the first half of today and we'll talk about like the basics of
what is the genomic variance what is varying calling and how gatk
works also together with other programs like like in general how how this thing works um and also during
today and also during tomorrow uh we'll run some interactive practices uh what i mean by that is we literally
type in some code and see if jt can respond to us um and if this throws us
errors or something like that so during these practices after today and tomorrow what i'm
expecting to see is we should set up a gatk
pipeline on hoffman that will go from rao sequence to a vcf
for a few individuals so for the assignment for this workshop i don't mean i don't really want to
throw you some very new uh like super big data set um so if you have
uh downloaded this data set that i shared with you that will be the data you can work on or
if you have your own data like so say right now you have some bond files you want to make vcs based on that you can work on that
too um so for the like i think for those of you for getting grades um
other than the attendance uh you're going to be graded based on the assignment and also like a small quiz
by the end of tomorrow um so for the assignment is as simple as by the end of the day we
get a vcf output and if so if we can get that everything looks good we're happy so the
assignment and also the quest both of them are not going to be due until literally the end of this week
so you have i know some of the analysis on gatk may take a few hours and especially if you're running two errors
it may take some time to debug so you you guys all have the end of sunday to to show me that you
have your output and you turn in the quiz so the quiz will be another google form that i will send out and
i'll send that out after we finish everything by the end of tomorrow and you you can finish that in class or you can
take it home and fill it up before uh before next week all right
so um so let's start with some of the the basics with uh genomic variants
um so i think uh from what i from what eloy told me uh all of you
guys have taken a ngs workshop before or something equivalent to that
so you should know a little bit about like how like a fast q file looks like and maybe
even how bomb file looks like so we know that those files they cover this information for the entire genome
so say for talking about humans which is the organism i'm most familiar with so most of the examples i'm going to
give here are based on human if you need some examples with some other stuff so i can i can probably talk
about something about mice but not really about plants anyway so for humans our genome is about
like three database in size so that that's that's a lot of information so if you're talking about
like sequences like if you're looking at our fastq files or the bom files for humans
that's a lot and if we have several individuals um we're talking about a lot of like
disk storage uh realistically when we study it say a population
um what you're interested in most of the time it's not like what exactly are these three gay
base pairs like what they are is in sequence and what genes they called most of the time what we're interested
in is the difference between individuals or between populations because
we know that most of our genomes are very conservative it is not just a conservative between
human individuals it's also a lot of them are almost identical shared across
species so some um like fun fact about like how
conservative our genomes could be we know that among humans 99.9
of genomes are identical um we know that between us and chimpanzees it's also like almost like 99 are
identical um actually between us and banana guess how much we share we share 40 percent so that's that's how
how conservative genomes are um so when we come down to like most we're interested in human
populations we're looking at diseases we're looking at our biological variations what we're most interested in is just
this point one percent so that's why we want to do genomic variant calling which is we want to identify what this
point one percent of the difference are there on our genome because ultimately those are the ones
that contribute to the all this phenotypical geno or genetic variations that we see among
us and also like if we're interested in like real what real world questions like disease risks
um evolutionary histories this point one percent is really what matters
so genomic variant calling is just one way of saying we want to find
out what this point one percent are and where they're located um
so for if we're looking at our genome there's all different sort of variations we can carry um the simplest
type is literally you have one base pair that is different between two individuals or a few
individuals so if we see differences between like like this point mutations like the original from point mutation but
then eventually we just see this one base pair differences across many individuals we call those
single nucleotide polymorphism well or sometimes we call that snaps
um so what we're seeing here is like eventually in those vcl files this
is very similar to what we're going to see there so what we're seeing here is we're looking at um this is uh some like a small set of
the sequence in drosophila or fruit fly uh individuals so here we're looking at the positions
so there are like maybe 20 something positions here and we know what is the um
um uh like what like what is the nucleotide for this
position in um the say uh most of the individuals
and then we have three populations here so they represent three um i think
it's not just three populations there's probably different subspecies here uh i forgot what exactly
this table is about but anyway we can think of as three species um so we see that you know a lot of
these positions they share what most individuals carry at this allele
so and it is represented by this little dash line here so what it means is for this population
everybody here carry this uh allele that we see maybe in the
reference genome and then also in most of the individuals in this species but if we look at another population
maybe some of them don't have exactly what other others carry
so in this case we call this set a variant and in this case this is a snip
variant so if you look at all of this side some of the sides may not be a variant in a given
population but if you look across populations then they may become a variant so in
population genetics we also call this type of variance like as long as they're not fixed completely like if we
consider this a population then all of these are variants they're segregating which means
their their frequency is not zero or one but then if we look at this
population specifically like if you ignore the others some of this may no longer be variance in those cases we don't call
them segregating sites and one unique thing here is for this one
in particular it is a variant but if we're looking at just of this population the reason is a
variant because uh this t is different from the c in the reference genome but um like if you're familiar with
some basic population genetics term uh in this case we call that this very uh this snip
is actually fixed in this population it's not fixed if we expand our scope
and look at all these three since it's fixed here it is not a segregating set in terms of this
population but then if we consider everybody all together it's still a segregating site so this is just something that um in
case it may get confusing here and there this is something to clarify so anyway what i'm trying to say here is
snip is one of the most common genomic variant and the term variant is actually a
relative term depending on which individuals you're looking at so something may be a variant um in one population but it may not be
when in another population so um yes so it's each in the previous slide
what's the heading like abc is each fly yeah so this is just like uh like
you can call it individual one two three four so that's the this is
the last column is uh yeah we don't really need this here but uh this is saying whether or
not this mutation is non-synonymous or synonymous so this is more like we are considering
this being like a like a mutation in a protein coding region whether or not they will confer a difference in terms of the the
the coding product yeah so i like yeah so so we don't really need
this here like this is just one example that i find maybe straightforward to illustrate what a
snip yes um so there are also different type of
genomic variants sometimes it's more than just one base pair that is involved so whenever there's a variant that
involves more than one base pair we call that a structural variation because it
it will change a structure of the genome so whether or not it is like just a few base pairs or it's
like longer than that in any case we can group them together um they're called structural variation
and they're just in contrast to the snips like like a different group of genomic
variants there are all different ways of like like having this structural variation uh i'm not
going to go into too much of the details here it's just like for your
interest in case you uh like i think some of you may be very familiar with this if you have taken
genetics classes some of you may not be so you can have a set of a sequence and with the
mutation that actually insert another sequence in it so in that case we call that insertion
the opposite of that happening is you start it with sql selectives and then suddenly you're missing this whole chunk
in that case we call it a deletion you can also have a sequence that doesn't change in length
it's just like simply this part that's swapped it can happen at times um so we call
that inversion so like visually they look identical but
some of the sequence is actually like swapped in order uh sometimes you may have like one part
that keeps repeating itself and result in this copy number variation or sometimes it's just like one time it duplicates
each other um so anyway these are all different ways of having structural variations sometimes you can
you may have even structural variation on the like on on a scale of chromosome like say you
have an entire chromosome that duplicates or missing in in all of these cases we call them
genomic variants um but in terms of this workshop like when we're trying to use
gatk to call or to identify this genomic variants we are not interested in all of them
because when we're having like more than one small part of the genome involved like
when we have like some copy number variation we have like a whole chromosome structural variation it's actually very
hard to map them um so structural variation is a whole different type of
class um and and we we don't really talk about that here so
when we come down to like using gatk to try to code some of the variants uh most of the time we're focusing on
snips and we can also cover some of those short variants so if it's an insertion
or deletion that doesn't involve like say some megabase of of the genome if it's just say like
some tens of base pair or some hundreds of base pair we can still map them fairly well and
identify them so in any case we will call snips and some short insertions and deletions
well insertion deletion you will call them indels so snips plus indels they're in general
generally speaking short variants and those are the ones that for the gatk is powerful at identifying
so if you're interested in other type of genomic variation like those copy number variations like those other
type of structural variations you may want to use a different type of tool um so for
gatk okay first of all it focuses on short variance another term we focus on is it
identifies like or this for this workshop we're using a tool in jtk that identifies
germline short variant um like like germination for variance so
what is germline mutations or germline variants um like as the name indicates uh germline
mutations are the mutations that happens in the germ cells or sperms or eggs um because those are
the cells that are involved in the reproduction um whatever mutation that happened to
the the germ cells are the ones that will get passed down to the next generation
so in terms of like genetics when we're talking about like like changes over generations changes
between populations we're interested in the ones that are inheritable like we want to see
like change like revolution of this variance uh over time and over like like space
scales so most of the time we're interested in this germ limitations um so there's another group of
mutations that doesn't happen to germ cell in which case if they happen to any
other body cell except sperms and eggs we call those somatic mutations
so those also happens all the time every time individuals have a cancer most of the
time it's because of mutations to the to the body cells like depending on wherever they are
um so somatic mutations or semantic variants are very important because a lot of
times they're involved in cancers and other diseases but since
they're not germ cells they don't get passed on through generations so gat does have a tool
that help you identify somatic mutations if that's something of interest in your in your research but
that is not something we're interested in for this specific workshop so for us for today and tomorrow we're
interested in using gatk to identify germline short variants
or snips and indels how why are the techniques different for
these mutations i mean the same tools can identify either mutation right
that's a great question um
i think well we can't we can go back to the gatk page they have a they have a good explanation on that
uh intuitively speaking i think that has something to do with your sequence uh
like i think like i think if you're interested in somatic variants uh the type of sequence you're
gonna obtain and also uh like even like the mapping process
may be different um i don't really work with somatic variation so i don't really have a great answer for that
um but i think that's that's a great question and we can go back to jtk page and see what exactly those two uh
the two tools vary um so so i don't want to give a firm answer
here because i don't have exactly that answer in my mind but yeah that we can i can find out that
quickly and send that back to you after after today
um okay so um um for uh
uh for the type of files we're interested in uh we know that before when we're
looking at like the raw sequences that are in the fastq files and when we try to map them to a
reference genome we get some sun file and also bond file for the genomic variants
since there's it's just like a small number of them this file that we're dealing with is much smaller than a bomb file or
fastq files so uh this the representation for this variance
are in the file that we call vcf uh this is literally like some uh variance
uh files that that that show you the variance um so which means for the gtk tool that
we're using to identify um this variance we're essentially trying to call this uh
variance in in our raw sequence and produce them in this vcf format
so um i don't know if everyone here have seen a vcf before it looks to me from the google survey
that i did some of you have seen it some of you haven't but anyway this is a screenshot of a vcf file
this is something from from my own research question i'm just taking a screenshot here so all of the
vcfs are almost identical in two ways um they're the basic structure for vcf is
at first if you open a vcf file you can open them in excel or you can open them in r uh in any case
you open you open this files you first see a bunch of lines with this double hash
actually so i think since i'm sharing all of my screen it might be easier to look at that here okay this is one of
the vcl vcf files from my work you open this and at first you'll see this double hash
stuffs like a lot like after maybe some a few hundreds of lines you started with something else so we
call this everything started with two uh hash we call those header lines so what they are is they're
essentially comments there are comments that give you information about how the cvcf file is generated what type
of format it's in even like like when you're seeing some acronyms later on
what they represent what type of individuals are here uh how many chromosomes are included um
and even like what type of commands you use to generate these vcfs like over time so they're all included here most of the
time we don't like if you're just looking at the variance you don't really need to look at these headers sometimes even for
for your own convenience when you're trying to manipulate things like in python you are you may even want to get rid of these
headers but they are useful because sometimes when you're looking at something down here um you want to reverse like using an
acronym you're not sure what they are you go back here and find like those comments so after the two
uh hash eventually you'll come to one line that started with one pound sign so that
is the start of the vcf and when you're starting with one hash it means like here here you go that we
save started and this is the column names or the labels for everything you're gonna see below
so all of the vcfs the first nine columns uh are identical
so if you're looking at this knight um they're like all of the vcfs no matter what species what populations what like tools
you use they always started with this first nine columns so what they are the first one
is which chromosome in this song the second is the genomic position so it depends
depending on the reference genome you use these positions may vary a little bit
but generally speaking they started from a small number to a large number along the chromosome
you also will see this id um column which actually so
if it's a snip or if it's a short variant that it has been profiled before um usually
for for this uh variance they have been given a name before so this is just a different way
of calling position one at this
how many is this like two around two megabase 2.5 megabase this is just a different way of calling
this thing so not all of the variants have an id so if it doesn't it will just it will
just be empty here with a little dot um but sometimes you can look up stuff
based on just these rsids or you can look things up by their uh relative like positions on on
the genome um the next two columns are the reference alleles and the
alternate allele uh i have a slight later that will cover what exactly yes i referenced earlier on
alternate allele generally speaking reference allele is what you see on the reference genome
and alternate allele is not what you're seeing reference genome something else um so
this would so usually here in the red line you only have one entry so you
can like it's either a snip or maybe it's like a short variant in any case you only have like one thing
in this column for the alternate ones it you not necessarily will have just one thing so if you just have like one
entry here it means for this specific locus you only have you only observe two different alleles
so we call those biologic sites you may run into this term here and there say sometimes we have a
raw vcf with all sort of variants and say we just want to keep the bioelect size
so when when you see that term say okay we just want to buy a link it means you want to filter them based on this
column here and you only want things that with only one entry in the alternate allele
column so when when there's something that is not biolic most of the time what you're seeing is
so i'm just gonna edit this here you may have see things like like this
so there will be other um um uh entries here that are separated by
a comma so usually when you see that what that means is for this position you see more than one
alternate allele in addition to the reference value you may see it maybe a c you may see an ac here or sometimes it's
even a longer thing so in so that's what these two columns are about
here is another column that is about the quality score so when we are calling vcf later we will
see that like eventually through all of these processes um the program would assign a quality
score for each of these calls so sometimes like like if you have really good high
quality genome like high coverage most of these quality scores are great um but
depending on the plus like where they are sometimes you may have this weird like a few contacts that
are not well aligned so you may have low quality scores or sometimes like depending on your
coverage if you have low coverage in the first place maybe most of the quality scores are bad
so those are some information that you can further use for you to filter the bcf later on like
depending on your research project so this is quality square here and here is also related to the quality
um it's it may not just be about a specific score uh sometimes we we use all different
sort of criteria and those we're gonna cover tomorrow like how we do filtering for vcf but anyway
you can assign a label under this and you can call them pass you can call them not pass or you can call them like
maybe it has a low score of something else so anyway you can assign your own labels here and this is
something that's just helpful for you for uh for you to manage the vcf like you may
not want to keep all of the sites you may want to you may want to get rid of some of the bad ones so this is just something that you can
refer to like you can you can filter based on the filter uh the filter label here
so the next column is usually really long so if you try to expand it you see that okay it doesn't even end
that it contains a lot of things so this is some meta information for the
population that you're interested in so this example here is a human population
um so in this info here you see this all this acronym and i may not remember all of them some
of these are the like a little frequencies uh allele count and uh what is a little frequency in all
different populations so all of these acronyms in the info part if you don't remember that's fine you
can refer them back to everything here so all of these things under info
you can find the respective information in your uh in the headers
um so most of the time depending on what exactly you're doing with the vcf
um this info column is not directly useful for if you're calculating like say
allele frequencies or other stuffs but at times say if you want to figure out
um for this population looking at what is the frequency in some other worldwide
populations you may not need to compute your own again you can look it up in the info column
or sometimes you want to figure out what is that allele in like the in the s what is the successful
allele in for for this uh population uh or for sorry for for this uh snip you can also
find out in this column so the next shared column here is called format
so what it is is it annotates what you're going to see in the rest of your uh
genotypes so always the first ones you're going to see is genotype and it may follow by
some other information that is related to this genotype so let's look at a different example
here this one looks better okay so this one here is a different vcf
so for here you can see that this format other than the genotype it also includes a bunch of other
informations um so i think i included an example here
uh that maybe we can see it more clearly if we if we uh open this up um
so this is just a zoom in of this cell here which is the same as this table that i'm
showing you here okay so if you're zooming at one of the cells what it is showing is everything is
separated by columns here so um if you look at things
like so there are like what like one two three four five different information
included in this genotype cell and what they are is the first one the gt represents for
genotype and an ad you can find it in the header ad is allele
depth and the next one is the total red death and also you have
the genotype quality you also have a fresco genotype likelihood okay so what
they are is we're saying that for this position there
there is a reference genome and there's alt sorry there's a reference allele there's an alternate allele
uh usually for the genotypes we call the reference alleles zeros so since all of the reference
entries there's only one entry here so there's only one zero here so all of this are the zeros
in the genome test that we're seeing and alternately all depending on how many entries are here
it is a number starting from one to whatever so say you have only one alternate allele then the one
here is going to be this one so so then for for this position for
example there are two type of alleles and we recall that this individual have
genotype 0 1 it means that for that individual at this position the genotype
is tg so it's just like a way like we don't want to write atcg here because that may
be very messy to look at we'll just use zero and ones to represent which alleles
these individuals carry um if you have more than one alternate allele so if it's not biolic so you have like
maybe a g here maybe like a gt here like maybe this is a structural variation uh in that case whatever the second one
is going to be two instead of one so you have zero one two sometimes you have
three maybe you can even have four um so this uh genotype this uh code here will just
represent which alternate allele you're you're looking at um this other informations
depending on again depending on what you're doing with the vcf they may or may not be useful so read
depth is later we're going to see that how we actually call this
genotypes it actually depends on so so you guys all know like this um
ngs class you see that for each position it has scanned multiple times in this uh
sequencing reads so say for this position this is a high coverage genome the overall read depth at this
at this position is 28 which means if you're looking at this bond file this this realignment you may count it 28 times
amount is 28 times 25 of the time you're counting zeros like or you're
seeing that in 25 of those reads you're seeing the reference allele
only three of them you are seeing the alternate allele but since you do see two of them alternating in this case
it called a this genotype here zero slash one so it's instead of
everything being reference allele it says this is a heterozygous here um so depending on um
like all the overall quality and also how many like route that they're there eventually you can assign you have
quality score through the program you don't need to worry about that here and the last one here is the pl
it may come useful depending on if you want to filter your vcf by um like how much do you believe
this genotype is really what it is so what it is is it is a minus 10 times a log
likelihood ratio of the probability of this genotype so the probability of
this of this genotype being this given the data you see so this is a
minus log likelihood which means um if you do like some quick math the lower the value
you see here the higher the probability this genotype is what it
is so uh you see three numbers here because you only have
two alleles it's either zero or once so everything is um
so we're talking about human here everything has like two alleles for each individual and you can only have like for all the
genotypes you can have is either zero zeros or zero ones or one ones so this is saying that given this
this minus uh this first scale likelihood the highest probability of this
likelihood is actually zero ones which is being called here and the chance
this uh this position may be actually a zero 0 is not super high
but it i mean you do see more zeros than once here and the chance this
is a 1 1 genotype is super low so we read this reversely the lower the number it is the
higher the probability of the genotype so the order of this is reference slash reference
reference slash alternate and alternate slash alternate so this is how we read the vcf um
uh like after you have seen a few of them in your own research it will get really clear like the first
night they're all shared and this the lot the from this column on is each column represents one individual
and most of the time what you're interested in is the genotype here yes so the third row
why does it say zero zero although it's g to t
um it says zero zero for this individual um it has an alternate allele and that
alternate allele may not be seen in every individual so usually you have a vcf
that is uh so this is a thousand genome human human project
you see a huge um like you can have like a lot of individuals you can have like literally
a thousand of them so the alternate allele may be seen somewhere among this
huge population but not in that given individual um so if you noticed another thing
that uh well now that i'm here already like i show you
two examples of vcf you may see that in some cases you see the
genotypes like the zero one zero zeros they're being separated by a slash
but sometimes you see things like this that are separated by uh how do you call this symbol like this
little line here so the difference between these two is whether or not you are calling
haplotypes in addition to the genotype so what what we mean by haplotype
is um for um if you're thinking about like like one
generation making another generation like like in this reproduction process we know that sperms and eggs they carry
literally half of your genomic information so uh which
uh of the so say you have like a few sites here um and they all have their own genotype
which ones like are segregating together versus the other uh we may or may not know so if we know
the haplotype which is we know uh well maybe here like if you're looking at this a few
like some of them are all zeros it doesn't really matter but some of them is like zero and ones uh we may not like
if we don't know the haplotype we know for this position at this individual it is zero ones
so there's there's two things that can happen here but we don't know which is going along with the rest of
the variance here um so in that case we have just a genotype we don't know the haplotype
so we call those type unphased so whenever you see a slash it means we're just in the genotype but
we can't call the haplotype yet um because we don't know which ones are set we don't have enough information yet
to know which ones are segregating together with others so this slash is called unphased
genotype um you see them a lot especially for uh whatever is being generated by gatk
everything you get is unfazed to call haplotype like to figure out which ones are
segregating together with others it involves another set of methods that
we're not going to cover here but just for your own interest this is a
separate analysis called haplotype estimation it involves a lot of statistical models
but anyway when you have a phased uh vcf it means that you can trust
this little line here so whatever on the left are being segregating together like they're
one haplotype and whatever on the right is one half protect so
this is something that you may notice when you read different types of vcfs
all right now let me just close this guys we don't need this anymore um
so another concept that is important when we're talking about different alleles there okay this
is not necessarily needed for the gate variant calling per se but
they're a important concept we're talking about vcfs so i think ultimately the goal here is
to generate vcf and to even understand what you can do with vcs so a lot of times we're talking about
we're using these names um we have just mentioned reference allele versus alternative
depending on whether or not you see that earlier on the reference genome there are all these other terms that
people also use so one of them is called major allele versus minor allele
so what that means is a major allele is literally the most common allele you see in a in a
given population for a given locus and whatever that is not a major allele um especially if it's
bialyc the other one we call that minor allele so you sometimes you may encounter this people ask you
look at this vcf get the minor allele frequencies okay then you're going to figure out like given this vcf
figure out first which one of the two alleles that you see less common and then that allele
frequency is the one you're looking at um a lot some other times people are
talking about ancestral alleles versus derived alleles so ancestral allele yes
for example your if you're in your question is human you're looking at humans and chimpanzees
we know that human chimps we share a common ancestor somewhere back there so whatever allele
that is observed in that last common ancestor we call that ancestral audios
and whatever happened on the specific state of specific human lineage in contrast to chimps we call that a
derivative so it is very easy to get confused with
them sometimes you may have a reference allele that is the major allele and also happen to be
ancestral but sometimes it may not be the case so every two
here are in contrast to each other but between the two sets sometimes you're talking about the same
thing sometimes you're not so they're not necessarily interchangeably useful uh
usable um so really depending on what you're talking about so for the vcf we're going to look at
which is the output of jtk we're only dealing with reference and alternate but just make
sure that in your own research question when people ask you figure out what is the ancestral frequency uh you
don't just take the reference you need to double check that the reference allele also needs to be the ancestral so this is just something
to keep in mind uh we seen we've seen this already uh
haplotype phasing okay um so uh depending on um your research uh
the reason why jtk hypotype or jtk variant calling is really important
is for example in my work i'm a population geneticist i work most of time with
publicly available data so i almost never need to deal with bonfire or fastq files
most of the time what i'm getting is already the vcfs so i most of the time work like i would say
99 of time i work with vcf and forward and it's only when i'm
looking at some really weird things like like i see something like outstanding on the vcf i'm not sure
if i trust that then i go back to the bomb file so really depending on your specific
research project um especially if you're dealing with a lot of publicly available data um vcs is
probably your best friend and so here we're just trying to understand overall
how in general we're getting the vcf files just in case even if you just you work
exclusively with vcf files at times you want to figure out if you want to trust
a specific genotype call and in that case you need to know how it went from the raw sequence all
the way to vcs so um for the rest of this workshop
we're gonna keep encountering several different type of uh file types um
i'm sure all of you have been familiar with like these three types here the the faster file which is the one
that we're going to encounter for the reference genome because for that one all we need is the
the sequence uh and also the fastq files which is the raw sequences you're going to
eventually generate variant calls from and we also have the bom file which is intermediate ones
which is this fastq files mapped against the reference genome so in your
ngs workshop you have covered all that so we're going to deal with two type of output
for the gitk workflow we mentioned what is a vcf file
and there's another type which is which looks almost identical to a reset file but slightly different
so that file is an intermediate output and which is the first output we're going to get from jtk it is called a
gvcf file so what g stands for is a instead of vcf it is a genomic
variant call format so it is called a vcf but it's actually confusing because it sounds
like this file also just includes the variance but instead this file includes the
genotype for all of your genomic positions so it includes variance and also the non-variance
so for vcf for example if you noticed like in the example i gave a few slides ago
um if you're looking at these positions they're not consecutive like you have positions like three
million whatever the next one is not instead of like four five one you have maybe like you skip like
16 positions and you have this in your vcf file it doesn't mean everything in the middle
does not exist they all exist what it means is all everything in the middle here
are not variants they all look identical and they all look like the reference area
so we don't since they're not variants we don't include those in the vcf but gvcf would contain
the information for every single position so if you're looking at a like this gvcf intermediate output
like this file is so much larger and all of these positions in theory are consecutive but
not the vcn file so for gatk this is our ultimate input
and this is our output and vcf file is the ultimate ones that we're interested in like we can
eventually ignore network get rid of the gvcf and we use gvsf to get a vcf calls
um so this is the gatk workflow that we're
interested in so it in general consists of three parts so um
depending on our schedule um we i i don't i think we can well cover
the first part we may cover cover some of this and the rest this part for sure we're gonna live on to tomorrow so so what it means is
it is this um flow chart tells us how we go from the xiao sequence reads
all the way to vcf so it includes three components the first component is
to get a bomb file that is good enough to call vcfs or to covariance
so in your ngs class you may have a work with with this part that you have your route
with in fast q files um you have your reference genome you map them against your reference genome
you get some bomb file you may not i'm not sure like i
correct if i'm wrong like i think you didn't cover in your ngs class that given a original bomb file how you
do some uh different like like alignments uh or calibration to get
a bomb file that is good for variant coding um so we're going to focus on here uh
especially for today that how we get a bomb file that is ready to go the next part is
the variant calling part so this is given we have this bond file that we generated from this first part
how we get the gvcf files and then eventually how we get vca files so after this part we'll get some vca
files that looks like they're ready for analysis but it's but before we actually use
those vcf for analysis um we need to actually look at remember
for the vcf files we have all these like columns that contains a quality so there's quality score there's also quality filters so
depending on what they look like you may want to further filter something out refine this vsa
files to make them actually ready for your own research so this is in general how
gtk work and for today we're just going to go from part to part to see how we set up codes for each part
of them um so we have three hours in total
now is we have past one hour do you guys want to take a 10 minute break and we come back here
because i mean for three hours i think what i'm thinking is we can take maybe two short breaks like at every one
hour just in case where like we get zoom fatigue um so
if that sounds good uh we can so right now is 232 what if we come back
here at 2 40 like like eight nine minutes yeah i'm gonna
pause the recording for now so you guys can go grab a coffee and do whatever and we're gonna be here at uh 2
40. okay so let's start back again
so where i was well one second let me share the screen
okay yes the screen sharing working for now okay good
um okay so what we're left with is this is the uh uh
this is the workflow for jtk so let's start with some integration
with variant calling so i think i kind of like like kind of like mention that already like
in what i was talking about vcs but anyway so like before we look at the specific
functions in gatk we wanted to understand like how variant calling in general works so we said that we
started with raw sequence in the fastq files we have the sequences and then
we can uh map them like using bwa for like for human-like organisms we map
them against the reference genome okay now we have raw sequences we know where they're lying and we have a bond file
um the next thing is we wanted to know before we get variant we wanted to know the genotype for all
of the positions which is similar to that gvcf file that i just mentioned earlier
so for all of these positions we wanted to know what the genotype is so then for for each of the given
position to figure out what is the genotype it is essentially looking at all of these dial sequence rules that
are stacked up at this position in your bond file and for this position that we're interested in like
what is the call in each of these reads so say if you say intermediately
coverage like say you have 15 weeds um so for for this 15 reasons
maybe all of them say one thing if that's the case we're good we have that geotag being i mean
depending on what that rate is it's either zero zeros or zero ones but in any case that is a
homozygous uh but if sometimes you have uh some of these say one thing someone
really say the other or someone will say even something else then we know that is
maybe a heterozygous whether or not it's a real heterozygous depending on the quality and also like how how this
reads align like so there are some hidden algorithms that deal with that but in general like if you intuitively think about how
we determine a genotype it is like so that we have a bond file that
is well clean that we trust and we just look at for each position what the reads are and depending on what
they are we call them different genotypes and then we once we have the genotype
reads for all of our individuals then we look across our samples so as i said
variant is a relative term it really depends on your population or individuals you you selected something
may or may not be a variant but even if it's not a variant all this information are already included
in this variant calling so say in the vcl file eventually you get you may cross off some things from the
gvcf that are non-variants but they actually do exist because you know that for the ones that are
eventually not included in the vcf they are just the reference allele so you can fill them up when you
try to merge vcfs between populations so if there's something that is not a variant in one population
but it is a variant in another and you want to merge them together to make one big vcf you can't fill those
missing parts up because they're not actually missing they are you know they're all zero zeros um so that's how vcs merging
works like you can manipulate these files eventually so this is our intuition with variant calling it sounds really
simple we just need to determine genotypes and then eventually we figure out which ones
vary which ones don't um so when we specifically
manipulate that manipulate that into atk we're essentially doing four major steps
so three steps of them are involved in gitk and there's one step i think you i'm pretty sure you
all have done that but i'm just gonna cover that briefly here in case um it's been a while since you take the ngs
class so the first step which is completely outside of jtk is
simply to map your reads to the reference genome the to generate the bomb file the second
part starts to involve gatk but not exactly uh which is to clean and prepare your
bum file so that it's good to call variants um so we're going to
show like what what what type of codes that is and the third part which is the first
main part that completely just involved g8k this part is to identify the genotypes
at all positions at each sample so this is a part where we're getting
gvcf's from the bomb file so there is one major function or program in g8k that we're
going to use which is called the haplotype caller so lastly we're again in jtk
we're going to consolidate all of this genie cf that we got from different samples and jointly call
variants among all samples in a given population cohort whatever you call that
so this is a process where we're going from gdcfs to vcfs so here this part
we're going to involve two functions in jtk one is dealing with how to
consolidate this gvsef together and the other is is about jointly called variance
given this consolidated gvcfs so that's sounds really simple so let's
look at specifically how to get that so um
um i'm not gonna go with like how you set up this uh some everybody know this already uh
just one thing that i will remind you is if you try to like do this interactive
practice make sure you ask for enough memories um i would say
at least ask for four gig of memories so that because git g runs in java um
and if it's too small it's not really gonna run so i figure this
set like this is a memory process it's a memory per given job this should be more than enough for
dealing with our practice data but if this is smaller than 4k if you
may have issues it should be it should take just a few seconds to get a node using this
so let's see this is what i have here i'm just let's uh we can do this together or you
can just see what i'm doing and i give you all my codes already you can copy paste them on
your on your own end like after after this but just i'm just trying to show like how
specifically this works so say i log into a node and i change directly to where i put all
the data um so um well i have i have changed into this
here already make sure like i think you all have access to this directory uh that's how
the scratch works i also just found out recently like i thought i need to just change my like 777 for everything but it turned
out oh everything is accessible in scratch um
so uh make sure when you work on this data you get a copy in your own directory
because this is the only copy i have so i'm trying not to uh
make something weird happen here um so before we do anything with this
directory um we can load all of these models um so those include
the bwa java the pie card which is the part that we're going to use to clean the bomb file also the jtk
itself um there's these two other things that may be useful some tools um just everywhere here know how to use
some tools like i hope you cover that in the ngs
and if not we can i mean i have some samtools code that i give as example
um so this is something that will just help us to manipulate the bomb file to view that because bomb file is in binary
format you can directly see what is what is in it this thing we're not gonna need this
yet but eventually once we have a vcf files we're gonna need some tools
to manipulate the vcf files um so there are different tools we can use
my favorite is bcf tools there's another very similar thing called vcf tools
uh you can load that tool it's also a model so if you do modular load vcf files sorry resafe tools you can
also get something so those we don't need those yet but tomorrow we'll need those so you can
just load them anyway it doesn't take anything so the first thing is we want to make sure that
everything we just loaded works or in another word we know they all work
but um nobody's gonna remember like all the like functions like like options like
like you need to type after you like after you call the program
so one easy thing to find out is it literally you call the program and ask you to to give your printout of
all the options you can't give there so for example this program is called pie card
pie card is it's a really useful tool for doing a lot of things specifically for our stuffs
this is we're going to use some functions in pi card to help us prepare a bomb file that is
good to go so if you literally just do java.jar
so this is where like this is the the path of where that
the javascript for pi card is located on huffman cluster so you can call this directly as is or
if you don't want to type a ton of things or if you don't want to copy paste this you can set your own path
for jtk for play card because for gitka it's the same thing that um hoffman is located somewhere
and you you can type that whole thing or you can explore your own path so it
saves your some typing time but anyway if i just copy paste this
and here we call that
what's going on here they are not request enough memory
um anyway so in theory this should give me a
a printout of what options are there in pie card let's see what out of memory may arrow
okay give me one second
let me request something again
just load all my modules
all right now go this
okay there you go okay i don't know what happened there anyway so this is when you're just
calling pie card it gives you all of the options it has so the ones we're going to use is
just like literally a couple of them we're going to use it to mark duplicates
which is here so if you do your command and another thing we're going to
use is to change the regroup like that's just a way to um
to change the annotation in your bum file um but the first thing we're going to use
is this so if you want to know all the options you can deal with with pycart
you can call pycard and call mark duplicates and it should give you all the options
that it requires um so this is just a test to see that pie cart works another thing
is for gatk so there are two ways to call jtk on hoffman one is very similar to how we call
pycard that we call java and we find where gtk is located
there are all different type of packages on gt of the atk on kaufman i would recommend to use gatk4 so i
think there are several versions of jtk 4 or hofmann anyone should work they're not that different but between gtk 4 and
jt 3 there's quite some difference so any of the gtk would work so if you just
do this it would give you a very similar printout as the pie card
there so that's you you're calling this through java another way of calling jtk
is since we loaded the jtk module already it means we can like bypass
java here and code jtk from there so if you copy paste this it will give
you exactly the same printout as just now see here so this is essentially doing the
same thing as what we just did so with this you you can see
all of the functions that you can call from jtk and then you can call them
specifically to see what what type of inputs it requires just because nobody remembers
any of this like options um i i never remember those so i use this as
a way to help me figure out okay which i'm going to use what type of input options are there
um so one thing specifically is of when you're calling jt cases it it
is essentially a java thing um you need to like you can't call jtk by itself it'll it'll give you an error
and ask you into specified java options so the only options it is mandatory to
specify is how much memory you need so that's why earlier we said well we want four gig of memory
so here you can do for gig or if you request it more on your interactive node or when you submit a job
you can put more here uh i think four gig for what we're doing should be enough so here
uh what i'm showing here is like a screenshot of the printout
um in case i hope it's all working on your end but if not like this is your reference
of how it should look like when you just call jtk by itself without specifying anything else
um so before we go into the details and especially after this workshop i'm
sure you're gonna work on your own for the git things uh your own research and i'm sure you're
gonna run into questions or errors or whatever things you wanna figure out that is not covered in
in this workshop so gatk website uh from the broad institute is your best
friend i wish when i was learning gatk i couldn't attend a workshop like this but i there wasn't
anything available so i literally learned everything through this website by myself uh which means you can do that too uh so
every time you run into questions uh or errors just google it and you can always refer
them back to the gatk website they have very very helpful tutorials
and also troubleshooting discussions that most of the questions
that you'll have can be answered through this website so this is just a really helpful
reference for your future use um it should have most of the things covered um the only uh
uh like tricky thing here is when you google your question uh you see things like
that are explained by the jtk website you need to double check if they're talking about gt s3 or g84
because as i mentioned earlier those two have like there are something quite different that
uh something that there's something you have to do in jtk3 but you no longer need to do that gtp4
um so yeah and it's like when you're trying to search things by yourself uh make sure that like it is talking
about jtg4 because they look very alike but they are slightly different
um so another some set of basic syntax that we can
look at is we can use send tools to view our bom file uh and eventually we're gonna need bcf
tools but so anyway so what i'm gonna show here is now i'm in my directory with all the
practice data you guys are going to need so if you look at what they are this is downloaded publicly available data
from the thousand genome project so for a thousand genome project most of the time like in my work for
example i deal with their vcfs but they also have all of their bomb files available
um so you can fully download those they're just they're just humongous um so clearly i'm not don't download all
of them so these are eight individuals uh so every three files is uh a set of individuals so this
is things for one individual another so there are eight of them um this includes the bomb file the bomb
index and also some other stuffs um and uh they are not the whole genome for these
18 individuals they are just the chromosome 20 which is conveniently provided
by a thousand genome already like they gave their chromosome 20 like in
addition to their whole genome um they did that i think it's for their
sanity checking things but for for us like this is a fairly small data set like
instead of downloading a few gig like each of them should be like 200 something megabytes
um so i figured this is a good practice set for our thing which means when we're
eventually calling vcf from these bomb files we're only going to get chromosome 20. we're not going to
get the entire genome um which is okay for practice sake but just keep that in mind
in your work most of the time what you're dealing with is a whole genome it's not just one chromosome
um so we want to maybe you want to just do some quick check what does bomb file
look like they look identical to any other bomb file you can think of
so you can use stem tools to build the first 10 record
to figure out at least okay you know for you started from about 60 uh
kb uh for the chromosome 20 and from then on and you can also use them tools to view
like specific range of chromosome 20. uh also make one thing you may want to like so
this is just showing the record of this uh way and not copy
where did it go it should be a small range yeah there you
go okay so for a small range like how this uh bomb file looks like um
so by now i think you all should be familiar very familiar with what these different columns are
anyway this is where your con your your read starts and this is the entire
read which chromosome it is um so one thing to
keep in mind for this specific practice data set is for this specific set
all these chromosomes are labeled as uh the chromosome like so instead of
like chr20 they call this just 20. which is fine um but this is something
that like if you're using your own like like human genome and if you look at like how
they're calling this chromosome sometimes they may or may not include this so it
doesn't matter right now but it matters when you're say you want to view a specific
interval of your your bond like here you're going to type 20 but if depending on how your uh sequence
is worked you may want to add the chr whatever they call this chromosomes uh so see here if i call this c
that chromosome 20 instead of just 20 it's gonna throw me arrows because you can't find this chromosome because this chromosome
is labeled just as funny here um so another thing is when you're using
a reference genome um for the human referential i'm using here it's also like i'm using the version
that it has um just like it doesn't have the this the string part for the chromosome um so
i mean this is some something really small like like i mean i noticed that when i was preparing for this
practice data set but i think that may be something that is common to throw your errors depending
on the data you have so sometimes the bond file you have like
if you download bim file from some source they may or may not have to buy uh index file so you can use some tools to
index the bom file that should be fairly fast um
so for bcf tools this is just like like we're going to use that to
manipulate our vcf files eventually and also there's like i'm going to mention somewhere that
there are some existing data that we need to use to do some calibration and that if you
want to view some a few records these are some sample bcf tools command um you can also like since you loaded
the bcf tools already you can literally type it and it's going to give you most of the things what you can do with this
you can view record you can sort them you can convert them and annotate it like
there's a bunch of things you can do with vcf tools but anyway this is some the basic syntax we're going to run into
um another really useful program that we're going to uh well i
i'm not going to talk too much about like igb here it's called integrative genomic viewer
so this is a really helpful software i don't know if in your ngs workshop they covered this
uh anyway this is a really useful program where it allows you to visualize your
bum file so instead of like looking them like this which is very hard to read it's almost impossible
you want to know exactly like how your how your wrists align to each other and if there's like sometimes you may
have a part of chromosome that is not well covered so in that case you download this
program um it i don't know if there there might be a linux version
i don't know how to do that so on my mac computer you can literally just download this as an app and you can load what is your
reference genome so in this case i'm using the human hd19 which is slightly older
uh coordinate system but it's not super outdated and what you do
is you load your bomb in this and you can see okay how your how reads are aligned
uh and if there's some part that's for example that is not well covered
um so if you try to load your entire bum file here like if it's
a whole genome even for just chromosome 20 this is going to take a lot of like you need to
like for the convenience if you want to do that in your local computer you don't want to download a few gig of things and load them all into your memory
it's the computer is probably gonna shot one thing that will be helpful is i use
this just for sanity check so say in retrospect i figure there's an
interval that i'm not sure what is going on i just extract them using samtools i
extract a specific region um on my from my bum file so that will be a really small file that i can easily
download and load them to igb to to literally see them um so
so for gatk variant calling this we don't necessarily need this but a lot of times when we're like i
feel most of the time we're doing research we're doing troubleshooting so this is just something that this is
where you can download this to your local computer and this is a good way to to do sanity
check so i'm not going to go through the
details of um the map reads uh because i assume by now you all
should know that uh and another reason why i'm not gonna give an example here is because i don't want to download the fastq file um
that's a lot of things so i'm just going to give the sample codes here this is how it works if you're like in your
research you're dealing with starting from the raw sequence um this is what you're going to need so first you download a reference genome
uh most like i mean unless you're dealing with some really rare uh study system
most of the organisms you're dealing with have a like quite a few reference genome that you can download so for human
um so the broad institute have a very good combo of resource that contains not just
a reference genome but also other stuff that we're going to encounter later but anyway we can download those
literally like we can choose a reference genome to download so i'm using hd19
um after you download that uh so i think the broad institute included their
the the index of the fafsa file but in case it doesn't you can create index under
bwa um and you can create like a like a uh like faster file file
uh under some tools and this is just how like and you can create a dictionary
for this so the faster the faster.fi and also the dictionary
these are essentially the three files you need for a reference genome so for our stuffs i did that all for you
already so if you go to the reference genome folder in this package that i gave you
it included this reference genome we're going to use so include the first file the file
and also the dictionary and also some other stuffs these three are the three things you
need for your reference genome directory so the human genome most of the times you
can download all three already you don't need to prepare them but sometimes you all you have is a faster file and you need to
prepare them a little bit so anyway so this is like if we go back to our general
directory we have our bam file here we have our reference genome under a different directory it doesn't
have to be a separate directory but just so if you're not meddling things together it's always clean to create a different
directory there um so
so and also here on the fast of fastest index file you can also see how
your reference genome is labeling their chromosomes so remember earlier i mentioned that in
the bomb file chromosome 20 is labeled as 20 not chr20
so in the reference genome you i also have this chromosomes that are labeled as just
numbers instead of like chr whatever so you need to you need to make sure that your reference
genomes index for the chromosomes or the contexts are the same as your bonfire context
labeling um it's easy to change that if they don't match but eventually they
need to match to to continue further and that's that's just a
common error source um so this is something you probably all
know already um you have your now you have prepared a reference genome
you have your first queue files for your raw reads you need to make a rao bom file
and this is where we're starting at and with clearly we didn't do that we downloaded a bum file already but this
is how this file should look like okay so the next is the real thing
is going to start the next part is we need to prepare our bomb file in several ways
the first thing of all that we need to do is we need to mark the duplicates or the
duplicate reads in our bond files so
that involves the pie cart um program that we just mentioned so under
pie card we saw that pie cart has a gazillion different type of programs and what
we're going to do is we're going to use the mark duplicates we're going to call this function so
this function takes one input which is just your bond file it gives you one output oh sorry two
outputs it gives you a one output that is like it gets rid of the the duplicates
and it also gives you a summary of what it did so these two that you're going to specify
here are the output in which case it's going to give you
a bump file that you you're going to use for your next steps so i just label this dw um the bomb file
and it's going to give you a sampled metric so this step it should be fairly fast to
run i can just run that quickly here so that you know how it works so uh i call my pie card
like you can type in your own and or you can copy paste this but i figured when you're learning uh
sometimes typing your own always help you figure out like what what exactly is going on it's okay a copy card a call mark
duplicates a specify my input which is this long name and i name it the output which is the
original name plus like i need to mark this and this is my output
all right let's just run this quickly it's gonna take maybe one minute no
it didn't work ah damn it what was that
memory thing again weird um okay i don't know what is going on i
can just request a little more memory
um i tested it earlier before the class started everything worked and i don't know why it keeps throwing me at
memory arrow but it may happen to you too so usually what i do
is for everything that i'm going to show as example i submit them as a job script so in the job you can request more
things uh you can request a little more resource than you actually need don't request way too
much that's gonna slow things down it's gonna make things like stuck in queue but
uh anyway let's see if it now allows me
to do this yeah i think now it's working okay
so this is the correct output of this process um you call these things
ask you to uh mark your duplicates and after a while
like it looks like it's all running there's no error if it doesn't if there's an actual arrow it's gonna
stop and you're gonna know so it looks like it's gonna finish
and i'm gonna show you what the output looks like
so also remember that when i specify the input like if you still remember how all my
files look like there are eight individuals so i'm doing each individuals one by one so this process you can do everything
all together you can do like just like like start all of these things you
can't do that you have to do them one by one so when you're doing the assignment like when you're trying to get
like prepare bomb file and also eventually get a vcf um depending on how your
job queues look like like if you don't have a lot of things running like you have a lot of resources open up
you can run all eight of them uh and give me a vcf that includes all eight that's fine um if
you have like like if some debugging is taking a long time and you just have time to run a few of
them i mean first of all you can parallelize them so you can submit one script that
like it takes different like like uh id names um so in theory as long as your
your uh hoffman can take say eight jobs altogether um it shouldn't take that long but
anyway if you have a few of them so it's a it's a cohort it's not just one individual
uh like we're gonna identify various amount of few individuals that's fine so if you give me like five individuals
that that's okay too but anyway i gave you eight even eight like in
practically they're not even considered a population but this is just some some some practice okay it looks like it
finished the first process so now if we look at our directory now it give us like in
addition to this original files we have it gives us a new bomb file and it gives us a
metric output so this bond file is what you're going to use for your
next steps so from now on the original this is original for this individual we no longer need this all we need is
this so um sometimes like so like like after this a few steps we're gonna
generate a few intermediate bomb file um what you can do is you keep the last
one like you keep the first one you keep the last one and after every step you if they're taking too much like like
disk space you can get rid of those intermediate ones um keep the original one because that's
the original one like if anything goes wrong you have your reference like like at least i can
start from scratch again um keep the last one like the ready to go bomb because that's the one
that goes into vcf so if you are doing like troubleshooting you you think the problem didn't come
from when you're preparing the bomb file you don't need to rerun this bomb cleaning again you can just go between bomb to like
couple type calling uh like the gitk part so so yeah so this is just like
we're going to generate a few intermediate things so with all eight individuals and remember
this is just chromosome 20. so if you're dealing with like a whole genome like each one file could be a like 30
gig um so you don't want to keep so many copies of those like they may take a lot of space
so keep the first and keep the last intermediate ones once you finish using them you can get rid of them um
okay so this is the first part we can mark duplicates now we generated a new bomb file the next thing
is it is not strictly necessary depending on how your original one file looked like but this
is just like something to like this is a step to annotate our bom files
we want to assign um uh in the uh individuals with uh
like what is their population name what is their individual id name so because sometimes your raw risk may
just come like fresh off the bench and individuals may just literally be
labeled like one two three four five if you want to rename them to something else um you can do that in this step
and if you want to assign them to a population name you can do that here too so here if you look at this
it calls pi card again it uses a different function called add
or replace real groups it takes one input which is the new bomb file you just generated
after you mark the duplicates and it's going to give you another bomb
output uh which you can label them as like a really grouped um dw like whatever bum file so it's
going to give you another bomb file here and the rest here is to specify how you
want to add or change your read groups so the first here is the population name
so your original bomb file may not include the information so you can add it here so
uh since i downloaded this data set from a thousand genomes and i know these are the british
individuals they are like i'm pretty sure there they included this already but i i mean in case it doesn't you can say
okay the population name is the the british like the gbr population from the thousand genome um
you can give it a library name um whatever you want to call this and also you can annotate which sequencing
platform it came off of so uh these ones they come from
illumina illumina um so you can write that here and also you can specify
um like in theory everything should be sorted by coordinates but in case they're not you can specify
how you want to sort things and also you can specify the platform unit there's also some
um like like like logistic things and lastly you specify your sample name
so here i mean this sample is already called this already but in case they're not if they're just like
number one then you can change your sample id here so this step should also be fairly fast
um so here i wrote this code that i called pie card called add or change groups input
output whatever else okay let's see if it runs
since it's running since this is really just a annotation part this step
is pretty fast okay let's leave it running and let's
continue on our end um so the next thing that
we're going to deal with in gatk which is actually one of the last step before we have this bomb file
ready to go is what we call base quality score recalibration uh the acronym is bqsr
uh later like after we have a vcf file we're gonna
deal with another function called vqsr so they sound really like they're really
alike but they're not exactly the same thing so and they're all in jtk which is confusing uh so just make sure like
you're calling the right thing here okay so what what is bqsr like why we need to do this
uh we have for example if you try to visualize our bum original bond file in igb we may see
that things look really messy like it doesn't really look like like how others are supposed to be like
like there are some parts like like there may be some like like this artifacts that it looks like a
variant but it may or may not actually be that so that is because i mean this is the nature of the raw
sequencing data um it may have a lot of like this systematic or machine errors
um made like from the sequencing process so you want to before you covariance
because those systematic errors may look like variants but they're not so you want to make sure
you get rid of those before you actually call the real variance so this is essentially what is
recalibration about it's like we want to identify what is a real variant what is
a artifact and we get rid of them um so that's what this process is all
about and and as gatk tells us like the especially for the short
variance calling process it relies heavily on the this quality scores so essentially what we're trying to do
is we want to train a machine learning model um to figure out
um like given the quality score and how variants look like in a set that we know
for sure these are the truth and we want to re-adjust like our sequencing data based on that
um so in case you guys are not familiar with machine learning model it sounds really fancy everybody talks about
machine learning these days um just a quick like recap of what machine
learning is about um you can think of machine learning as a dummy
that like or if you try to think about yourself like when you're really young when you're learning about
the world so say people tell you there's a category called fruit there's another
category called vegetable you don't really know what they are because at first those two categories
just sounds really abstract for you you look at some like an object in front of you you may not know if it's
fruit or vegetable so how do you figure those out so when we are learning like when we're
really young like we're giving examples so we're given that like look at an apple this is a fruit
look at a pear this is a fruit a banana is a fruit so you're given a lot of examples of what
fruit is and eventually in yourself you kind of figure okay i kind of figured some common theme
about what fruit is and then you're told a celery is a vegetable a cabbage is vegetable tomato is a
vegetable onion is a vegetable so then you also figure okay i kind of figured what vegetable is there may not be
they may not be that clear what they are but generally speaking so now if you're given like some like if
you're given a carrot and people ask you if this is a fruit vegetable given what you have seen before you
figure okay this most likely is a vegetable so that's how we learn things when we
were learning and for machine learning this is a very similar process it's at first you have a dummy model
that knows nothing it's just a thing like it's there so you give it data that with
labels that is like well labeled so you give it like this is a bad quality score this is a
good quality score and this is what they're associated with you get if after it has seen
enough examples it kind of like made like you kind of mold this model
into a thing that it can after you give another thing without a label it can give you a
classification of if it's a vegetable if it's a fruit so that's like a analogy of what machine learning
is about it needs to see a lot of real data with good labels to figure out uh how to make
a right decision between two classes so back to bqsr that was a long way of
saying what bqsr is is uh in gatk it can train a machine
learning model uh in which case you give it requires a set of um existing data
that uh from all other studies these are the data that we trust these
are for short variants and they're all associated with quality scores and how these variants look like
um so this is our our training data in this machine learning model so for human um again the broad
institute conveniently gave us a lot of information other than the reference genome so we can download
some like the the snip database and we can also download um uh intel database um
so it anyway those all gave us like like some existing sites of things that we we know
these are for sure variants uh they're good so those are the input for the machine learning model
so back to our data okay so first of all that add or replace
uh regroup process finish like after you see this message you know
it's done there's no error we're good and then if you look at the output it now gave us another new bomb file
like after this this is a new one file that is marked the duplicates are marked marked
up and the real groups are well labeled so this is the bomb file that we're
going to need for our bqsr process so now since we no longer need this if it's taking a lot of disk space
you can get rid of that or keep it depending on what would you prefer so
now if we go back to our folder but now we're talking about bqsr
if you go to this folder then the nonsense i downloaded
all of the snips and indels that have been identified in a thousand genome project
um so for i mean since we're using a thousand genome data
we can use their profile for for this for this step ideally we want to we want to use a
snip and indel uh profile from all human populations so there is such a
thing it's called dp snips it's a it's a database of all human short
variants i think current is hosted by ncbi you can download it directly from their ftp
um but that file is ridiculously big we don't necessarily need that here so
for our like to to make our practice like a like something manageable within
the next couple of days um i didn't download that part but we can also use that if you prefer
so we can use this um as our training data in this bqs machine
learning model so how does this work for also for other most of the other common study systems
you can download this uh short variance this non-site from some online platform
so for mouse you can use the standard database um i think for plans there should be
things like this similar tool i just don't know what exactly they are um anyway so going back to bqsr now that
we know this is uh our known like the training data how do we set how do we train a machine
learning model first of all so again here we come back to jtk
this is no longer in pi card in jtk we call the bqsr
function it's a base recalibrator we tell it what is our reference genome so we need
to give it the path of our reference that faster file like that that thing and the input is our
new bomb file that we just generated after the two cleaning steps and we need to specify
the known sites so um here we have two set of known
sites we have the snips when we have the indels there are two separate files so you can you can specify known size
twice if you have one thing you can just specify once so this part like this known size can be multiple
like this long story errors and the output instead of giving a new
one file just yet before that it actually so this step
only gives you a table so what it is is it this step trains a machinery model and
it tells you which part of your bom file needs to be recalibrated
so this table is a relatively small file it's not that big it's not even comparable to the bomb file size
but this process just remember it does not give you a new bomb file yet but it gives you a list of things in
this table that um that the recalibration needs to be done at so uh i gave you some sample command
for this process this process takes quite a while um i don't know i never finished this
for our sample data so i don't know how long exactly it takes to run this but since it's it it's related to
training and machine learning model it's it's gonna take a little bit at least not something we're gonna wait
here so you try this here i couldn't read file okay
i think i'm in the wrong folder uh now it should work
okay there it is working so you can watch this working or you can submit this as a job and
wait somewhere else and you don't have to watch this happening live but anyway this is
already showing you this training part is working it is going to eventually generate generate you a table but we're not going
to wait it here um do you guys want to take another break we're almost
done for the preparing the the the bomb file part what if we take
another short break now is 3 34 let's say 3 35
how about we take a short break we come back here at 3 45 p.m like in 10 minutes
okay so okay let me finish this bqsr part because we have a little
bit left and i think the rest we can just continue tomorrow since
most people left already okay so so this part and i think other people can catch up when
when they when they when they watch the video so when before we ended
uh for the break uh here is where we left off of like we say that we can train
a model under bqsr to figure out which things to recalibrate
and so we generated this table um so i can't really run the example here
because i didn't finish running this because this is gonna take a little bit of time
uh so anyway so after we train the model we have that table of which ones to
recalibrate now we can actually run the recalibration and generate a new bomb file
so what we do is we call jtk we have whatever java option and now
instead of doing the base calibrator function we actually apply the bqsr so we call this function
we specify the reference genome which is our reference faster file we specify our input which is our bom
file from the previous step after we mark the duplicates and after we run we add
the read group and now we tell it what is the input recalibration file which is this table
that we just generated from the last step so if we specify this
and now we say we're going to generate an output which is a bqsr calibrated new bom file so
this so i forgot how long this step takes um but all together these two steps
um may take anything between like an hour to more than that depending
on how big our original bond file is i think since now we only have one chromosome
this shouldn't take that long so what i want you guys to do is to
i gave you a sample commands here uh like with everything we have covered
in this class up until here to apply the bqsr run this on a few individuals that you
want to call variants from so i have those examples on this one individuals so you can set
set up a job request that does several individuals in parallel um so run those
and eventually this bomb file that this after the mark uh duplicates after add
group after bqs or recalibration this bomb file is the one that we're going to need for
calling the variance so does this sound good
if so if there's no more question i think we can safely end today's workshop
and tomorrow we're going to we're going to going to assume everybody have this bomb file that we
have cleaned up and this is ready to go and we're going to use that um to um to call the variants
so do i have any additional questions
um just a quick question can you i might have missed like can you tell like how the model is kind of
trained on the like the base recalibration yeah like the bcf
on the thousand genomes yeah so so if you look at this non wait am i still sharing my swing no
um okay are you seeing my terminal now yeah okay so if we go to this nonsense
and if you look at like what what i downloaded here so these are some vcf files in like
compressed terms so since vcf they're they're not binary those are real text files you can
literally use zls and look at how they look like so everything looks like a vcf it starts
with vcf headers and we just continue going keep going
so there so okay so now we start the actual vcf part
so this looks like a vcf except it doesn't have all the individuals so it has all of this so so this is the
in-depth indel file so it has all the like everything nothing is a snip so they're all like
small insertions or deletions um so this is a profile
of human indels from the thousand genome data so this is everything that after like
this studies have worked on this they trusted these are real variants and each
variance like we know how things look like and also we know what their quality score is
so i think what this machine learning is doing is it's trying to associate the pattern between the quality score um and also
the variance so that maybe like when when there is like a like dell you
shouldn't have a quality score being like zero or like or or something like really
like like off so like it's going to look at all of this uh trusted in dells
and figure out how a real indulge should look like and also we can similarly look at those
uh this snip data so snip data similarly like this is a
all the headers and now we come down all the snips so everything is like like there's one
entry in the reference and there's one entry in the an alternate these are all snips and they're all each associated with
quality scores and all this other information it has so i
um right now i can't really talk about like uh how exactly
uh uh this uh the underlying uh i don't know what
type of algorithm they're using this machine learning model but in general um they look at
this existing sites um and like these are the things we trust and it's also like it's trying to find
patterns between what its variants look like and their quality is worth so
so this is like after looking at all of these sites this model is going to have like a it
should have a trained model where it should like if you give it another site uh with a quality score it should
tell you whether or not this is a this is good or this is an artifact
so if you're interested in the underlying algorithm for this thing i think you can again go back to the gatk website they
should have a place where they talk about like what exactly is going on in this machine
learning model um from like just off of my head right now i can't really
say like what type of algorithm it is i mean i don't know which exactly is the machine learning model they used but
generally speaking it's looking at some trusted data and it's going to classify
your data yeah yeah that's helpful yeah um
so with this let's end today's thing here again for before tomorrow it'll be
really helpful if you can get a few of this cleaned bomb file so that we can use
them as example to go for the variant calling uh let's continue tomorrow and thanks for so much for
staying until now thanks yeah yeah yeah see you tomorrow bye